<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Sofia Baroudi</title>
    <link>https://sofiabaroudi.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Sofia Baroudi</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.148.2</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 21:30:23 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://sofiabaroudi.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>When Time Split</title>
      <link>https://sofiabaroudi.github.io/writings/when-time-split/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 21:30:23 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sofiabaroudi.github.io/writings/when-time-split/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I write because I find no solace in silence.I write because the shattered glass tells a story my voice cannot carry. August 4th 2020 marked itself in microseconds—first the stillness, then the pressure wave that turned every window in Beirut into deadly rain. I was in my car when the sky cracked open, when the ordinary afternoon transformed into a moment that would divide time into before and after.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sound came first, not as sound but as silence—a vacuum that pulled at my eardrums before the blast pushed everything sideways. The windshield held, barely, but spiderwebbed into a thousand crystalline paths. All around, the city&amp;rsquo;s glass skin fell like sharp snow.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Snu Stan Topez</title>
      <link>https://sofiabaroudi.github.io/photography/snu-stan-topez/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sofiabaroudi.github.io/photography/snu-stan-topez/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on Epicurus</title>
      <link>https://sofiabaroudi.github.io/writings/thoughts-epicurus/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sofiabaroudi.github.io/writings/thoughts-epicurus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am a true believer in Epicurius’ argument of the importance of esteeming, above all things, the simple pleasures of life. I also accept the imperative to cultivate a tranquility of spirit through the pursuit and enjoyment of those simple pleasures: “Hence a correct comprehension of the fact that death means nothing to us makes the mortal aspect of life pleasurable, not by conferring on us a boundless period of time but by removing the yearning for deathlessness.” His main point is not that accepting death necessarily leads to pleasure and happiness, but rather that rejecting “deathlessness” means accepting human frailty, developing an awareness of our limitations, and appreciating the small things in life as full of meaning. These are the tokens of being fully alive. I can’t help but wonder, though, would I be happier if I remained ignorant of death like the Biblical Adam and Eve? Does the “knowledge of [our] disease caus[ing] the death of many” give us any more pleasure in living or am I just choosing to ignore my inevitable fate? I for one accept the premise that the soul is as mortal as the body. “Everything fails and is found wanting at one and the same time,” Epicurius would say.
As it happens, absurdly, we all share the same experience of the human condition, which is characterized mainly by our fatality and at the same time our desire for meaning. This desire is a wanting to find something in us that escapes the regular cycle of nature, something that would allow us to enjoy the little idiosyncrasies of our human condition and most defiantly to find beauty in our meaningless life. This is not meant to sound pessimistic. On the contrary, I aim to spotlight the value of savant ignorance. Kundera says it better in The Book of Laughter and Forgetting when he writes, “It takes so little, so infinitely little, for a person to cross the border beyond which everything loses meaning: love, convictions, faith, history. Human life—and herein lies its secret— takes place in the immediate proximity of that border, even in the direct contact with it.” This makes me wonder; if our actions take place one inch away from the loss of meaning, what are we in this world, what is the essence of our living, of the meaning of being human? The great authors seem to answer, and I adopt their view, that the answer starts with an acknowledgment of mortality and the need to embrace, transcend, and live alongside the face of this absurdity, the inescapability of death. As a consequence, small things grow in importance and joy. A quiet, simple dinner with family. A warm bath. A long conversation with a missed friend. Reading a good book. Watching a sunset. Seeing things, the way I do through my camera lens. I mean seeing things in a new light. To look at something is very different from seeing it. One does not gain deep insight until you apprehend beauty against the certainty of death. This is the moment when beauty comes into existence. I believe this process of thinking makes us particularly, specifically human, a process that requires will, imagination, and a tolerance of ambiguity in order to see in things not as what nature formed objectively but as what we endeavor to form subjectively. Perhaps the only reason we see is that as human beings, we seek to make the best out of our mortality, to eke out meaning from the deep void, to allow every bit of life to fill our body and “souls” with suffering, achievement, pleasure, satisfaction.
There is a specific painting that comes to mind and commands my attention every time I think about the relation between pleasure and death, Renoir’s Dance at Bougival. The lady in the red hat, joyful and shy as she dances while following her partner’s lead, represents a side of&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://sofiabaroudi.github.io/photography/mam_incapri/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sofiabaroudi.github.io/photography/mam_incapri/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;title: &amp;ldquo;Mam in Capri&amp;rdquo;
date: 2023-07-18            # or any date you like
cover:
image: &amp;ldquo;cover.JPG&amp;rdquo;        # exact file name from step 3
caption: &amp;ldquo;Capri, July 2023&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
